all right y'all let's learn how to write
a long essay question or leq for APUSH
AP World or AP Euro it's the same rubric
for all of them so everything I'm going
to say applies to whatever course you're
in and depending on your persuasion this
might be the most difficult essay you
have to write on your AP exam because
look at it just sitting there judging
you you don't know anything about this
topic do you you do there are no
documents no help you just have to crack
open those brain folds and start writing
so how do you do that how do you get a
perfect score on the stinking leq well
I'm about to tell you so if you're ready
to get them brain cows milk let's get to
it so the leq is the last thing you're
going to have to do on your exam and
you're going to have 40 minutes to write
it you'll have already passed through
the multiple choice and the short answer
questions and the DBQ and if at that
point you have any shred of life and
human dignity remaining in your soul
then you have what it takes to earn a
perfect score in this essay which would
be a six and before I get into the steps
for writing you should know that the
College Board tells you ahead of time
from which periods they're going to be
pulling these questions it's not a
mystery it's right in their course and
exam descriptions and here it is in a
satisfying little chart you can see that
they're going to give you three options
and you only have to write one so make
sure you choose the one that you know
know the most about okay now let me just
quickly mention that if you need more
help that I'm going to give you in this
video then you should check out my apsa
crem course it goes into much greater
depth on how to write dbqs leqs and saqs
for AP World AP US and AP Europe it's
got examples for every point on the
rubrics and that will show you what
earns the point and what doesn't plus
there's videos from this guy that you're
not going to find here on YouTube so if
you're struggling with these essays that
might be the thing to help you so Link
in the description below okay now let's
get to the steps for writing this essay
step one read The Prompt just like on
the DBQ your first task is to read The
Prompt and when I say read it I mean
really read it like understand what it's
asking Mark it up and I emphasize this
because as I never Tire of reminding you
when you're under pressure you are
dumber than you think that's not an
insult it's just a fact of the universe
so take a minute and really read it and
when you do you're going to be basically
looking for three things all of which
you need to mark on the paper it don't
be the guy who's like yeah well whatever
I can remember it all no you can't write
it down now the first thing you need to
Mark in the prompt is the time period
they give you remember if you write the
most brilliant essay that has ever been
written in the history of History
writing but you're talking about the
wrong time period no points for you and
trust me here as someone who has scored
these essays for the national exam one
of the most frequent mistake students
make is to write outside the time period
that's given but not you my dear pupil
not you you are going to mark That Thing
Up you are going to underline that time
period And if they give you a time
period in centuries you're going to
write out the numbers remember Under
Pressure your IQ declines precipitously
so when you see the 20th century write
out the 1900s next to it just so you
don't get confused now the second thing
you want to Mark is the historical
thinking skill they want you to write
with so notice here they explicitly
mentioned causation that means your
essay needs to be a causation essay and
if it's not it's going to be hard to
earn any points and sometimes the AP
overlords like to try to confuse you for
example look at these prompts from the
2022 a push exam in all of them they
want you to evaluate the relative
importance of causes of different events
so although you will be talking about
causes it's really a comparison essay
you're comparing the different causes
and making an argument for which of them
is most important so Mark the historical
thinking skill because that's the skill
that needs to frame your entire essay
third Mark the categories they give you
to write about this one wants you to
compare the French Revolution and the
Revolutions of 18 48 this one wants you
to compare economic developments in
different parts of Europe so don't write
an essay comparing social or political
developments and the way to save
yourself from such an egregious mistake
is by marking up the prompt all right
step two get a six okay now that you've
understood the prompt and what they're
asking you to write about you need to
understand the rubric and the points
that you can earn the first point you
can earn is for a thesis and you can get
one point for this now in order to get
that juicy Point your thesis has to do
two things first it must be historically
defensible that just means that your
thesis has to make an argument like it
has to take a St so for the first a push
prompt for 2020 to you have to take a
stand among the causes of migration
during that period were religious
freedom and Economic Opportunity so you
can't just say two causes for population
movement were religious freedom and
Economic Opportunity that is an argument
but it's not the kind of argument
they're asking you to make you have to
choose which one is more important and
then go with that now the second thing
your thesis needs to do is establish a
line of reasoning this means you have to
show how you're going to defend your
argument and for this stuff some
vocabulary in there like you can't just
say there were many significant
similarities between the French
Revolution and the Revolutions of 1848 I
mean yeah technically that is an
argument but you have to to be specific
like what similarities are you talking
about like name them get specific so to
ensure you do these things within your
thesis let me give you a formula which
goes like this restate the important
parts of the prompt because A and B and
here A and B represent the specific
pieces of evidence that you're going to
use to support your thesis so going back
to the 2022 aush prompt here's an
example of this formula in action
population movement to Colonial British
colonies occurred mainly for economic
reasons because of the pilgrims
religious freedom in Holland and the
purely economic nature of James town so
I made an argument here and I
established a line of reasoning here so
I'm going to argue in this essay that
religious freedom wasn't actually a
significant cause of migration and here
are the two pieces of evidence I'm going
to use and that smells like a point to
me okay the second point in the rubric
is for contextualization and for this
one you can earn one point and
essentially what they're asking you to
do here is to put the argument of your
thesis in its larger historical context
and the rubric says that you can do this
before during or after the prompt you
know you do you boo but I have never
seen anyone successfully contextualized
during or after the period so my advice
is to contextualize before the period
that you're writing about I think that
just makes more natural sense to us so
what you're going to want to do here is
to write one paragraph probably you know
three to four sentences that sets the
stage for your argument and don't go
back too far in time only something like
50 to 100 years there are no hard fast
rules on this but in general the closer
you are to the time period you're
writing about the better there are two
things to mention here that are going to
be the difference between a point and no
point number one make sure you use
specific historical evidence and number
two make sure the evidence or historical
developments you describe are relevant
to the prompt so just make sure to be
specific use vocabulary words here don't
just talk in generalities okay now the
next part of the rubric is the evidence
section and here you can earn up to two
points you can get one point for
describing two pieces of evidence
related to The Prompt or you can get two
points for supporting your argument with
two pieces of evidence okay now let me
show you the difference between
describing evidence and supporting an
argument with evidence to describe
evidence that's relevant to the prompt
you just need to name it and then Define
it so if one of your pieces of evidence
is imperialism then I just named it and
now I say which is when one nation
extends political or economic control
over another Nation okay and in that I
just described the evidence but hey
you're not here just to describe
evidence baby you're here to get get all
the points in this section so let me
show you how to support an argument with
evidence and to set you up for this let
me suggest a paragraph structure that's
going to help you form an argument first
write a topic sentence this is going to
be one of your sub arguments that you
named in your thesis either the a or the
B as my friend Rachel Carr always says
your topic sentence always needs to
steal from your thesis so let's use this
prompt from the 2022 AP Euro exam for an
example evaluate the most significant
similarity between the French Revolution
of 1789 to 1799 and the Revolutions of
1848 so let's say my thesis goes
something like this the most significant
similarity between the French revolution
in the Revolutions of 1848 was the call
from the lower classes for Liberal
reforms and their ultimate failure after
the installation of a conservative ruler
so my first paragraph will have a topic
sentence like this both the French
Revolution and the Revolutions of 1848
began with calls for Liberal reforms
from the lower class then I need to
continue the paragraph with my evidence
I'll talk about the three Estates in
France and the marginalization of the
Third Estate and the extravagant
spending of Louis the 14th which created
economic chaos in France and then I'll
talk about the reforms demanded by the
Third Estate Etc and all the while I'm
going to be demonstrating how these
pieces of evidence Pro prove my topic
sentence and thus my thesis that's
important always tie your evidence back
to your thesis and then my second
paragraph is going to deal with the
installation of conservative rulers so
I'll talk about Napoleon after the
French Revolution he'll be a complex one
because in many ways he upheld the
Revolutionary gains and in other ways he
did not and I'll talk about Napoleon
thei and on an on so that is how you
structure a paragraph that makes an
argument okay now let's move on to the
last section of the rubric the analysis
and reasoning section in which you can
earn up to two points the first point is
awarded for your use of historical
reasoning so basically this point is
awarded for doing what the prompt told
you to do like if the prompt is a
causation question then you'll get this
point if you successfully write an essay
demonstrating causation and the same
with change or comparison or whatever
and look that's about as complicated as
this point gets like did you perform the
historical thinking skill that they
asked you to perform if you structured
your thesis and your paragraphs like I
showed you it will be very hard to miss
this point now the second point in this
section is awarded for complexity and
you can get one point for this and
they've given you like six different
ways to earn this point and that's all
very complicated but by far the easiest
and most straightforward is right here
if you use at least four pieces of
evidence throughout your essay to
demonstrate a nuanced understanding then
you'll at this point and that's kind of
vague but my advice is to do this make
sure two pieces of evidence support your
argument while two pieces of evidence
challenge your argument and again that's
not required this is just my advice so
if you're writing a causation essay then
two pieces of evidence need to support
your argument that X caused y while the
other two pieces need to acknowledge
that Z caused y but just make sure you
explain why you think that X is a better
explanation for the causation than Z
okay well click here to watch my other
videos on writing that go in depth into
the various skills and points needed you
can click here for my apsa crem course
which will take you through every point
of the rubric with examples for each so
you can feel confident in writing for
this course thanks for coming around and
I'll catch you on the flipflop I'm Lou